<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on dsgarage.org</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on dsgarage.org</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>G2P Whitepaper</title>
      <link>/post/g2p-whitepaper/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 13:56:34 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/g2p-whitepaper/</guid>
      <description>In 2014, Dr. Margolin, Dr. Stuart and Dr. Ellrott wrote a draft white paper outlining the need for a computational model to efficiently communicate known Genotype/Phenotype association. This working group would eventually evolve into Variant Interpretation for Cancer Consortium VICC.
Many of the ideas and goals changed of the project changed over the years. Below is the original whitepaper draft, to show how much the project has evolved.
GA4GH Genotypes to Phenotypes (G2P) Task Team Motivation One of the most important goals driving the collection of genome sequence information is to understand how particular variants lead to observable phenotypes and treatment options.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Handling Failures from OpenStack Swift in Funnel</title>
      <link>/post/network-failures/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/network-failures/</guid>
      <description>Handling Failures from OpenStack Swift in Funnel When building distributed services, handling failures from other services is a fact of life.
We use OpenStack Swift as our object storage service, and we use Funnel to transfer thousands of objects to and from Swift. Failed transfers have been common; the Swift server ca be unavailable, overloaded, and even lose chunks of data during upload.
It’s been challenging to make Funnel tolerant to all these failures, improved our logs and tools available for debugging, improved our code, and we’ve learned a lot along the way.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>