<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Systems | Data Science Garage</title>
    <link>https://ellrottlab.org/tag/data-systems/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://ellrottlab.org/tag/data-systems/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Data Systems</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Jan 2019 10:27:20 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://ellrottlab.org/media/icon_hufdd866d90d76849587aac6fbf27da1ac_464_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Data Systems</title>
      <link>https://ellrottlab.org/tag/data-systems/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>AnVIL</title>
      <link>https://ellrottlab.org/project/anvil/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jan 2019 10:27:20 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ellrottlab.org/project/anvil/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The NHGRI Genomic Data Science Analysis, Visualization, and Informatics Lab-Space (AnVIL) is a
project to build a data commons to allow researchers to efficiently analyze and visualize
genomics data on the cloud.
This project is a collaboration with Oregon Health and Science University, University of California Santa Cruz,
University of Chicago, The Broad Institute, Washington University in St. Louis, Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Johns Hopkins University and Pennsylvania State University.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Grip</title>
      <link>https://ellrottlab.org/project/grip/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Aug 2018 23:19:31 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ellrottlab.org/project/grip/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BMEG</title>
      <link>https://ellrottlab.org/project/bmeg/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ellrottlab.org/project/bmeg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The BioMedical Evidence Graph (BMEG) integrates different types of biomedical data into a unified graph for efficient application of machine learning and discovery algorithms across heterogeneous data types. BMEG will leverage the petabytes of genomics data available for tumor samples from repositories like the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cancer.gov/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;National Cancer Institute&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://gdc.cancer.gov/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Genomic Data Commons&lt;/a&gt; to predict drug sensitivity, patient outcomes, and other clinically relevant phenotypes.
The BMEG data model is instantiated in a scalable graph database optimized for storing and querying graphs containing terabytes of vertices and edges distributed across a multi-machine cluster.   This graph is the store of record for the BMEG. It maintains the connections between projects, donors, samples, molecular data and treatment evidence and assures that these entities are associated correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Funnel</title>
      <link>https://ellrottlab.org/project/funnel/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ellrottlab.org/project/funnel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ohsu-comp-bio.github.io/funnel/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://ohsu-comp-bio.github.io/funnel/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funnel is a toolkit for distributed task execution with a simple API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A task describes metadata, state, input/output files, resource requests, commands, and logs. The task API has four actions: create, get, list, and cancel. Given a task, Funnel will queue it, schedule it to a worker, and track its state and logs. A worker will download input files, run a sequence of Docker containers, upload output files, and emits events and logs along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A wide variety of options make Funnel easily adaptable:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BoltDB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elasticsearch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MongoDB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AWS Batch, S3, DynamoDB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OpenStack Swift&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google Cloud Storage, Datastore&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kafka&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HPC support: HTCondor, Slurm, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and more&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
